Guide to the Americas collection, 1811-1920 MS 518
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Americas collection
1811-1920
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Levander, Caroline
MS 518
3 Linear Feet (5 boxes and digital objects)
Original letters, broadsides, pamphlets, printed materials and books documenting the 19th century and early 20th century political and cultural relationships between the United States, Mexico, Central and South America, Cuba, Spain, and Portugal.
Historical Sketch
The Americas collection strives to represent the full range and complexity of the Americas. Thomas Jefferson famously observed that "America has a hemisphere to itself," and the founding fathers agreed that gaining influence in Spanish America "piece by piece" was essential to the U.S. Conversely, Latin American nations like Brazil, Cuba, Nicaragua, and El Salvador used the American Revolution as a touchstone for their own nation formations, even as they aspired to shape the U.S. democratic model to their own needs.
This story of national exchange and influence across the hemisphere will be more fully told through this archive which brings together key documents. Currently scholars interested in telling this rich story must travel, for example, between the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C. and the Cuban Society of Historical and International Study in Havana. A notable exception is the University of Maryland's Early Americas Digital Archive, which invites scholars to submit their editions of early Americas texts for digital publication. Its historical range of 1492 to 1800 makes it an ideal future partner for Rice's initiative, which begins with the heyday of nation formation from 1776 to 1815 and ends with the building of the Panama Canal in the early twentieth century.
This archive will allow us to understand, for example, why Brazilian insurgents owned and read copies of the American Declaration of Independence as well as works by Jefferson and Thomas Paine; why José Martí found the U.S. system of governance a rich source of commentary and critique for Cuban independence efforts; and why Fidel Castro quoted the American Declaration of Independence and likened the burning of cane fields to the Boston Tea Party during his 1958 take over of Cuba. But such an archive will also allow us to think in new ways about the U.S. American story. It will show us, for example, that U.S. slaves escaped South as well as North, establishing communities throughout Spanish America during the U.S. antebellum period. Such an archive, in short, brings into sharp focus the overlapping national stories of the hemisphere.
Historical sketch excerpted from text courtesy of Dr. Caroline Levander, Humanities Research Center, Rice University.
Scope and Contents
Original letters, broadsides, pamphlets, printed materials and books documenting the political and cultural relationships between the United States, Mexico, Central and South America, Cuba, Spain, and Portugal, beginning with the heyday of nation formation from 1776 to 1815 and ending with the building of the Panama Canal in the early twentieth century. Many of the documents are original government publications such as constitutions, decrees, or presidential and congressional messages, and broadsides and pamphlets serving as public statements regarding the political and social events of the time. Other items of note include George F. Dunham's "A Journey to Brazil on the Good Ship Montpelier," an 1853 first hand description of slavery and plantation life in Brazil, and the first Mexico City printing (1821) of Augustin de Iturbide's Plan de Iguala.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center in the vault.
Acquisition Information
This material was purchased from a manuscripts dealer in 2005, in collaboration with the HumanitiesResearch Center, Rice University, under the direction of Dr. Caroline Levander.
Arrangement
Arranged by country, where the country is the main subject of the material. The last series is "Multi-country", where one country writes to or about another. Arrangement within each series is chronological.
Missing Title
Series I. South America, 1812-1861
Series II: Central America, 1821-1829,1861-1920
Series III: Mexico, 1821-1865
Series IV: United States, 1823-1893
Series V: Cuba, 1896
Series VI: Spain, 1812
Series VII: Portugal, 1822
Series VIII: Multi-country, 1811-1914
General Note
Portions of this collection are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/35298
Index Terms
Subjects
Plantation life; Slavery; Nationalism -- History; Mexican War (1846-1848); Politics and government; Presidents; Revolution (Texas: 1835-1836)
Document Types
documents; pamphlets; broadsides (notices); corrrespondence
Places
Guatemala; Mexico; Argentina; Bolivia; Brazil; Chile; Cuba; Texas; Spain; Portugal; Peru; Venezuela; Texas -- Goliad; United States
Subjects (Persons)
Dunham, George F.; Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849; Iturbide, Agustín de, 1783-1824; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Tyler, John, 1790-1862
Subjects (Corporations)
Isthmian Canal Commission (U.S.).
- Series I: South America, 1812-1861; 242517
  - Subseries A: Argentina, 1815-1820, 242535
    - Alvarez, Ignacio. El Director Interino del Estado en Buenos-Aires á Los Habitantes de Todas las Provincias. Buenos Aires: Niños Expósitos, Aug. 26, 1815. Rallying support for the independence movement in Buenos Aires. 2 pp. (Br #10), 242540 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Manifesto Que Hace A Las Naciones El Congreso General Constituyente De Las Provincias-Unidas Del Rio De La Plata, Sobre El Tratamento Y Cruel-Dades Que Han Sufrido De Los Españoles, Y Motivado La Declaracion De Su Indenpendencia.Buenos Aires: Self wrappers. Contemporary ownership signature on verso of last leaf. Fine. In a half morocco box. An important manifesto by one of the first states in Latin America to fully establish freedom from Spain. The "Imprenta de la Independencia" published this pamphlet in the year following Argentinean independence." 11 pp. (PD #23), 242539 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1819. Constitucion de las Provincias unidas en sud-America, sancionada y mandada publicar por el sobrerano congreso general constituyente en 22 de abril de 1819. Buenos Aires: small quarto. Modern vellum over boards, spine and covers gilt. 20th century bookplate of Adofo Garreton, accompanied by a typed note in Spanish indication this copy had belonged to Juan Antonio Garreton, an official of the 1824 Congreso General Constituyente, whose manuscript notes are found periodically in the text. [2], iv, 71 pp. (PD #16), 242538 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Diaz Velez, Eustoquio. Bando. Don Eustoquio Diaz Velez Coronel Mayor De Los Exercitos De La Patria, Ayudante Comandante General Del Estado Mayor General En La Comandancia De Armas, Gobernador Intendente Interino De Esta Provincia Y Delegado De Correos & C. & C. Por Quanto En Oficio De Ayer Me Ha Comunicado El Sr. Secretario De Estado En El Departamiento De Dobierno El Supremo Auto Del Tenor Siguiente., 242537 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Manifesto De La Honorable Junta De Representantes De La Provincia De Buenos-Aires A Todas Las Demas Hermanos [caption title]. [Buenos Aires] A manifesto from the legislative body of Buenos Aires regarding the state of the nation. [4] pp. (PD #24), 242536 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B: Bolivia, 1825-1854, 242533
    - Proyecto de Constitucion para la Republica de Bolivia y discurso del Libertador. Buenos Aires. Ediciones de la Imprenta de Hallet y Ca…#11. 32 pp. (Pm, #28), 242534 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries C: Brazil, 1831-1853, 242530
    - 1831. Printed document. O Brasil Imperio: e o Brasil republica. Reflexoes politicas offerecidas aos brasileiros amantes da sua patria. Philadelphia. Favoring independence and constitutional monarchy, recounting the events in Portugal and Brazil that led to Brazilian independence. First, possibly only edition. 89 pp., 242532 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1853. Dunham, George F. "A Journey To Brazil Aboard The Good Ship Montpelier. Captain Swift." 228 pp., 242531 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Subseries D: Chile, 1822-1833, 242524
    - Constitucion politica del estado de Chile. Promulgada el 23 de octubre de 1822. [Santiago de Chile]: Imprenta del Estado. First edition of the first full-scale Chilean constitution. 78 pp. (PD #40), 242529 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [1824].Constitucion Politica Del estado De Chile. Promulgada En 29 De Diciembre De 1823. Santiago de Chile. Small quarto. The third Chilean constitution. 81 pp. (PD, #25), 242528 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - [1828]. Constitucion politica de la Republica de Chile. [Santiago de Chile]: R. Rengifo. Large woodcut vignette on title page. 35 pp. Likely the first edition of the 1828 constitution. The finest achievement of the regime of Francisco Antonio Pinto, the constitution provides for popular elections at the national level and a system of checks and balances. (PD, # 41), 242527 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - [1832] Proyecto de reforma de la Constitucion. 30 pp., 242526 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [1833] Constitucion de la Republica de Chile jurada y promulgada el 25 de mayo 1833. 48 pp., 242525 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries E: Peru, 1825-1826, 242521
    - [4-27-1825]. Gaceta Extraordinaria del Gobierno. Lima: Imprenta del Gobierno. #37. 12.25 x 8 inches. Announcing to Peruvians the state of peace reigning throughout the American continent. 2 pp. (B, #18), 242523 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - [1826]. Constitucion para la Republica Peruana. Lima: Imprenta de la Libertad, por Jose Maria Masias, 1826. 120 pp. First printing of independent Peru's first constitution. (B, #8), 242522 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subseries F: Venezuela, 1812-186, 242518
    - [1812]. The Venezuelan Declaration of Independence and Constitution. First Edition. London: Editions by Longman and Co. Paternoster-Row. XXIII + 309 pp. (B, # 29), 242520 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - [12-18-1861]. Letter: Ayers Braach & Co., re. Failure at setting up a sewing machine business in Venezuela as "the people of this country are not sensible enough…" Caracas, Venezuela. To I.M.Singer & Co. 1 p. (ALS, #39), 242519 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series II: Central America, 1821-1829,1861-1920; 242464
  - Subseries: Guatemala, 1821-1829, 242469
    - [4-10-1821]. Guatemala. Havitantes de la provincial de Guatemala. [in text, at end: Guatemala [sic]: 10 de abril de 1821]. Praising the Captaincy-general of Guatemala for their loyalty to the crown and condemns Mexico's Agustin de Iturbide. 3 pp. (PD, #2), 242516 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - [9-15-1821]. Gainza, Gabino. Manifesto del gefe político á los ciudadanos de Guatemala. [in text, at end: Guatemala: 15 de Septiembre de 1821]. His recounting of the meeting that led to the Declaration. 3 pp. (PD, #4), 242515 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - [9-16-1821]. Gainza, Gabino. El dia 15 del corriente se acordó lo que sigue: Palacio Nacional de Guatemala quince de septiembre de mil ochocientos veinte uno. Siendo públicos é indudables los deseos de independencia del gobierno Español…. Declaration of Independence of Guatemala. 3 pp. (PD, #3), 242514 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Sub-subseries I: 1822-1829. Collection of printed materials documenting the tribulations of the early years of nation-building following independence from Spain. Guatemala and Xilotepque. In Spanish. (Arc, #5), 242470
      - Item 1. Ganiza, Gavino. [Guatemala, 2-21-1822]. Broadside. [drop-title] El Serenisimo Sr. Generalisimo Almirante, en oficio de 23 de Enero proximo pasado, que he recibido hoy, se sirve comunicarme haberse dignado disponer la Serenisima Regencia Gobernadora del Imperio, que por ahora, y mientras no se disponga otra cosa, continùe yo con el mando que obtengo en esta Provincia en calidad de Capitan General interino. Folio. 1p., 242513 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Item 2. Velasco. [Guatemala, 7-19-1823] Broadside. [drop-title] Los Señores Secretarios de la Asamblea nacional constituyents me han dirijido la órden que sigue: En secion de 14 de este mes acordó la Asamblea nacional constituyente: que el Supremo poder executive haga imprimir y circular la nota de las comisiones ordinaries de la Asamblea, previniendo á los gefes y corporaciones politicas de provincial. Folio. 2 pp., 242512 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Item 3. Molina, Pedro, et al. [Guatemala, 7-10-1823]. Broadsheet. Ciudadanos de las provincias unidas del Centro de America. [Begins:] Vuestro poder executive se halla instalado[.] Llegó ya el dia en que escuchaceis la voz de vuestros conciudadanos, que revestidos por vosotros mismos del supremo poder darán cumplimiento à la èxpression de vuetra voluntad, declarada por la asamblea nacional constituyente. Folio. 3 pp., 242511 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Item 4. Filisola, Vicente. [Guatemala, 6-3-1823]. Broadsheet. [drop-title] Habiendo remitido al Exmo. Señor Marques de Vivanco con fecha 1 [primero] de Abril último mi decreto de 29 de Marzo, lo pasó al Exmo. Señor Ministro de Estado y del Despacho de relaciones interiors y exteriors, quien despues de dar cuenta al Soberano Congreso constituyente me dice en contestacion lo que sigue: Por los oficios de V.S. al Exmo. Sr. Marques de Vivanco de I [primero] y 10 del pasado, se há enterado el Supremo Poder ejecutivo del estado político de esa Capital, y de las ledidas tomadas por V.S. con motivo de los simultaneous movimientos, así del Exército libertador, como de la mayoria de las Provincias… Folio. 3pp., 242510 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Item 5. [Guatemala, 5-5-1824]. Secretaria de la Asamblea nacional constituyente. Broadside. [drop-title] Tablaáque deben arreglarse los partidos de la provincial de Costa Rica para la eleccion de diputados á su legislatura. Folio. 1 p., 242509 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Item 6. [Guatemala, 5-5-1824] Secretaria de la Asamblea nacional constituyente. Broadside. Tabla á que deben arreglarse los partidos de la provincial de Costa Rica para la eleccion de diputados á su legislatura. Large folio. 1 p., 242508 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Item 7. Valle, Jose del, et al. [Guatemala, 5-20-1824] Broadsheet. Manifesto del gobierno supreme de los Estados del Centro de America. [Begins:] La Asamblea Constituyente da decretado las Bases de la Constitucion politica y acordado el metodo con que deben ser elegidos los gefes y representantes de estos Estados. Folio. 4 pp., 242507 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Item 8. [President]. [Guatemala:] Arevalso [4-18-1824]. Broadsheet. El gefe político superior y la Diputacion Provincial de Guatemala á los pueblos de su comprencion. [Begins:] Desde el feliz suceso de nuestra independencia, ha considerado el Supremo Gobierno de absoluta necesidad atender con preferencia al resguardo de nuestros puertos, precaviendo de esta suerte los males que acaso por nuetra emancipacion intentaria hacernos la nacion de quien antes dependiamos. Folio. Attempt to preserve. 3pp., 242506 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Item 9.1824. [Puigsesver, Felipe]. [Guatemala:] Imp. Nueva que dirije J.J. de Arévalo, 1824. Parafrasi o glosa de la carta del apostol San Judas Tadeo a todos los fieles… Small 4to. Modern wrappers. Light waterstains. 33 pp., 242505 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Item 10. [11-6-1824] [Saldana, Jose I.] [Guatemala:] Imprente J.J. de Arevalo. 8vo. Reply to J.S. Cañas' Advertencia patriotica. Important Church-State relations controversy. Modern wrappers. 12 pp., 242504 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Item 11. 1824. [Santa Maria, Jose Andres de]. Gautemala: Beteta, 1824. Pamphlet. [drop-title] Impugnacion del manifiesto del gobierno de San Salvador sobre la justificacion de la errecion de aquel Nuevo obispado… 8vo. Modern wrappers. Light waterstains. 21 pp., 242503 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Item 12. Beteta. 5-7-1824 – 4-9-1825. Gaceta del Gobierno Supremo de Guatemala. A collection of various issues, including a special issue (No. 33) on the Battle of Ayacucho and the end of Spanish rule in South America. Numbers 9 (pp.61-68), 11 (pp.77-84) [incomplete], 13 (pp. 103-104 and 111-12) [incomplete], 14 (pp. 113-19 and 121-26) [incomplete], 15 (pp. 127-36), 19 (pp. 161-70), 23 (pp. 193-200), 28 (pp. 235-40, 243-44) [incomplete], 33 (pp. 271-72), 34 (pp. 309-10), 40 (pp. 311-18). Modern wrappers. Missing a few pages. 4to., 242502 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Item 13. Arce, Manuel José. [Guatemala, 8-9-1825]. Broadside. El Presidente de la Republica a los Centro-Americanos. [Begins:] Conciudadanos: se acerca la hora de dejar el reposo; de empuñar la espada que tanto tiempo hace teneis dispuesta, y de prepararos à la defenza de vuestra libertad que comienza à ser amenazada y que sera siempre gloriosa y triunfante. Folio. Attempt to preserve. 1 p., 242501 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Item 14. Sosa. [Guatemala, 12-28-1825]. Pamphlet. [drop-title] Reglamento del Senado de la República federal de Centroamérica. Folio. 9 pp., 242500 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Item 15. [9-1-1825] Arce, Manuel José. [Guatemala:] Union, a cargo de J.J. de Arevalo. Pamphlet. El Presidente de la Republica a los Centro-Americanos., 242499 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Item 16. [President] [Guatemala, 12-31-1825] Broadsheet. El gefe del estado de Guatemala a sus habitantes. [Begins:] Colocado el Gobierno al frente de la administracion pública y teniendo à su cargo la de la hacienda, conoció desde luego que sus ingresos no eran bastantes á cubrir sus erogaciones. Folio. 3pp., 242498 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Item 17. 1825. Santa María, José Andrés de. Guatemala: Beteta. Pamphlet. Desngaño [sic] religioso al pueblo Guat. Small quarto. The schismatic question of the bishopric of San Salvador. Modern wrappers. Light waterstains. 58 pp., 242497 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Item 18. F.X.B. Guatemala: Imp. De la Union, 1826. Broadsheet. Ciudadano Licenciado M.Q.H. [Begins:] Mui Señor mio: para contester a su pregunta sobre la election de Canonigos que ha hecho el Ciudadano Ahierdi… Folio. 2 pp., 242496 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Item 19. Castillo. [San Martin Xilotepeque, 9-30-1826] Broadsheet. …Decreto El Vice Gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislative tubo á bien decretar y el Consejo sanciono lo que sigue. [Begins:] La Asamblea legislative del Estado de Guatemala considerando: que el Estado ha sido atacado y hollados sus fueros escandalosamente por el presidente de la república: que en tales procedimientos se ve peligrar su independencia y el systems federal que felismente nos rige. Folio. 2 pp., 242495 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Item 20. 1826 [Secretaria de la Asamblea del Estado.] [Guatemala, 9-4-1826] Broadsheet. [drop-title] Tabla que manifesta los representantes que deben renovarse en la Asamblea del Estado para la legisliatura del año entrante de 1827… Folio. 2 pp., 242494 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Item 21. Castillo. [San Martin Xilotepe`que, 9-22-126] Broadside. … Decreto. El C. Vice Gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislative tubo á bien decretar y, el Consejo Representativo sancionar lo siguente. [Begins:] La Asambléa legislative del Estado de Guatemala [sic], teniendo en concideracion las criticas sircunstancias en que se haya el mismo Estado: amenazada su existencia politica por la autoridad ejecutiva de la republica, y siendo un deber del cuerpo Legislativo dictar todos las resoluciones combenientes à fin de reponer las cosas al Estado constitucional, ha tenido à bien decretar y decreta. Folio. 1p., 242493 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Item 22. Leon, Juan Jose de. [Guatemala, 5-22-1826] Broadside. … Decreto. El Gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislative tubo à bien decretar lo que sigue. [Begins:] La Asamblea Legislativa del Estado de Guatemala, haviendo tomado en concideracion la renuncia que el C. Anselmo Quiros hizo de la plaza de magistrado suplente de la Corte Superior de Justicia, y advirtiendo que los Ciudadanos Manuel Beteta, Marcelo Molina, y Simón Vasconcelos, suplentes así mismo de dicho tribunal no tienen la edad que la Constitucion prefija para estos destinos… Folio. 1p., 242492 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Item 23. Leon, Juan Jose de. [Guatemala, 5-10-1826] Broadside. … Decreto. El gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislative tubo à bien decretar, lo que sigue. [Begins:] La Asamblea legislative del Estado de Guatemala, considerando legal la escusa del Ciudadano. Manuel Francisco Pabon para no admitir la fiscalia de la Corte Superior de justicia, para que se le nombrò en decreto de 28 de abril último, por no tener la edad que la ley previene para estos destinos, ha tenido a bien nombrar en su lugar [sic] al Ciudadano Domingo Cortés; y en consecuencia decreta… Folio. 1p., 242491 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Item 24. Cortés, Domingo. [Guatemala, 7-22-1826] Broadside. … Decreto. El gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asambléa legislativa tubo à bien decretar y el Consejo Representativo sancionar lo siguiente. [Begins:] La Asamblea Legislativa del Estado de Guatemala, considerando: que interin no este organizada la milicia active puede el Comandante general desempeñar las funciones de inspector, y consultando al menor gravamen possible del erario, ha tenido à bien decretar y decreta… Folio. 1 p., 242490 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Item 25. Cortés, Domingo. [Guatemala, 7-22-1826] Broadside. … Decreto. El gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislativa tubo a bien decretar lo que sigue. [Begins:] La Asamblea Legislativa del estado de Guatemala, teniendo en concideracion que el decreto número 18 dado por la Asamblea constituyente no expresa si el tambor maior y pìfanos que componen parte de la plana maior en la milicia active deban ser veteranos; teniendo presente que lo han sido en las milicias disiplinadas y que éstas plazes son necesarias para la fuerza del Estado, ha tenido a bien decetar y decreta…. Folio. 1p., 242489 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Item 26. Leon, Juan José de. [Guatemala, 5-22-1826] Broadside. … Decreto. El gefe del Estado de Guatemala. Por cuanto la Asamblea legislativa tubo à bien decretar lo que sigue. [Begins:] La Asamblea Legislativa del estado de Guatemala, conciderando: que por decreto de la Asamblea Nacional constituyente de 13 de Enero de 1824, se mandarin establecer catedras de filosofia en todos los pueblos de los Estados donde se puedan dotar, ó los maestros que quieran enseñar gratuitamente: que la habilitacion de los maestros cuando no sean bachilleres en la facultad, se comete por esta ley a las disputacions provinciales. Folio. 1p., 242488 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Item 27. Payes, Domingo, et al. [Guatemala, 5-20-1826] Broadside. Aviso al publico. [Begins:] Por commission de la Municiplaidad, los que subscrivimos, estamos encargados para cuidar de los que enfermen de sarampion, en el barrio de San Sebastian… Folio. 1p., 242487 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Item 28. 1826 S. Francisco, Manuel Garcia Lego de. Guatemala: Impr. Mayor, Casa de Porras, [1826]. Pamphlet. Reflecsiones [sic] sobre el artículo primero del decreto emitido por la asamblea de Guatemala en veinte de Julio de 1826. Small quarto. Prohibits young men from entering the religious orders before age 23 and from taking final vows until age 25. Significant Church-State controversy. Modern wrappers. Stains. Decorative paste-over on the title page. 15 pp., 242486 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Item 29. 1826 [Secretaría General del Gobierno] [Guatemala]: Beteta [1826] Pamphlet. Memoria que presenta a la asamblea legislative el secretario general del gobierno del Estado de Guatemala. Al abrirse las sesiones del año de 1826. Small quarto. Important annual report. Modern wrappers. 19 pp., 242485 (Box 2, Folder 12)